<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The inheritance of the saints in light set forth in a sermon preach'd at Whitehall, August 11, 1700 / by Ab. Campion ...</title>
            <author>Campion, Abraham, d. 1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12687009</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12687009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 346:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The inheritance of the saints in light set forth in a sermon preach'd at Whitehall, August 11, 1700 / by Ab. Campion ...</title>
                  <author>Campion, Abraham, d. 1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Leake for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preach'd at Whitehall, before the Lords justices.</note>
                  <note>"Publish'd by order of the Lords justices"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65791:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Inheritance of the Saints in Light;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth in a SERMON Preach'd at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> Auguſt 11. 1700.</p>
            <p>By <hi>AB. CAMPION,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd by Order of the Lords Iuſtices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Leake,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:65791:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65791:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>COLOSSIANS I. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Giving thanks unto the Father, who hath made us meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words ſtand here as a great inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Duty, <hi>to walk worthy of the Lord in all well pleaſing.</hi> And as a Sovereign Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial to ſupport the Spirits of Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſharpeſt Trials; to bear them not only with Patience but with Joy and Thankſgiving, as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text informs us.</p>
            <p>It is the Chriſtian Faith only that can with good Reaſon Adminiſter ſuch comfort under the Croſſes of this World; becauſe how afflictive ſoever they may ſometimes appear to ſenſe or vulgar apprehenſion, yet if compared to the Goſpel-Treaſures, the Joys above, they are light, very light.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the Afflictions of this Life, nothing (I think) pierces more to the quick than the loſs of a Perſon dear to us, eſpecially when it ſurprizes. And yet if God think fit, to tear from our boſoms the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of our Eyes, the Darling of our Souls; our Church has directed us in her Funeral-Service (ſo full of Faith is her Holy Office,) to give God thanks for the Cloudy paſſage of his Providence. It is a ſtrong
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65791:3"/>Combate between Fleſh and Spirit, when we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged thus to thank him with Tears in our Eyes; but Faith will juſtifie it.</p>
            <p>The Great Diſpoſer of all things has at this time call'd us of this Nation to a Signal Exerciſe of this Faith, by an amazing Providence, <hi>on a ſudden</hi> ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from our Embraces our young <hi>Joſiah,</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the preſent, the great Hope of the future Age. We had not time to think, not time to <hi>Pray,</hi> to hold, if poſſible, the Almighty's Hand: Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Vertue is ſeldom long-liv'd; it is often dangerous to be loved too much. The Divine Jealouſie will not permit us to be confident in Man; for this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perhaps not long ſince we met with a very fatal diſappointment of our Hopes. This Stroak, ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other, is ſo much the more ſevere; we can ſcarce diſcern the <hi>Fathers</hi> hand, it looks ſo very angry. And yet we are ſure God is always Good, whether we are ready with our Reaſons or no. Can we then heartily thank God for this? We have done it already at his much lamented Funerals; and if Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven exceeds the Earth, we had reaſon ſo to do.</p>
            <p>We Inhabitants of Earth are apt to be too partial to our preſent ſtate of Things. Such is our fond ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration for Earthly Treaſures, tho' we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as perhaps to pity the hard Fate of this young Prince, for being deprived of ſo near a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a Crown. Fooliſh pity! Such ſhort think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betrays the ſleepineſs of Reaſon as well as Faith, not conſidering the Scene is now ſo chang'd, that whatever Delight He might once take in his Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Birth-right, Earthly Crowns now appear deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his Eye, who is admitted into that Heavenly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65791:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Inheritance of Light, my Text holds forth to us. The Advance is His, the Loſs is only ours.</p>
            <p>Many may be the Great Conſequences of this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Stroak as to us, but it is not my buſineſs here to inſtruct in Politicks, or to provoke your Paſſions by a Panegyrick; rather, as my Text directs, to excite your Faith, and deſcry what Comfort is thence to be derived under this, and all our greateſt Calamities. When our Affairs here afford us no good proſpect, look up, our Faith will never fail us. The more tottering our Condition ſeems here to be, the greater reaſon we have to give God thanks for the hopes of an Eternal Inheritance, which in the Goſpel is brought to light.</p>
            <p>What Rewards God has treaſured up for good Men in the other World, was the grand Diſcovery the Son of God came from Heaven to make. He ſcatter'd the Clouds with which the face of Heaven was covered, and aſſured the World of that Eternal Life, of which they had before but faint and wavering expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Some Philoſophers have obſerv'd, that of all the habitable Globes of the World, the Earth only is wrap'd in Clouds, made thereby a proper Seat for Sinners. A fit Emblem of Man's moral State and Condition. Thoſe Clouds hanging in the Air as a Curtain drawn to ſhut them out from the ſight of Heaven; being alſo Treaſures of God's Vengeance hovering over their guilty heads, from whence do ſometimes iſſue Storms and Tempeſts, and many of the moſt dreadful Calamities which Sin has brought upon the Earth, and its Inhabitants. But what e'er becomes of this Philoſophical Notion, the Clouds
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65791:4"/>which do more fatally veil the face of Heaven from the Sinner, are thoſe which lie upon his own Heart, his Luſts and Paſſions. Theſe do ſo blind the Eye of Humane Reaſon, as that it can neither diſcern the Light, nor reliſh the Joys of the Heavenly Manſions, nor the beauty of that Holineſs which leads thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The Spiritual Happineſs of Heaven does no more affect a vitiated Palat, than painted Glories: And the Conditions upon which the Goſpel has propoſed its Immortal Crowns are to the Sinner perfect fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs. <hi>The pure in heart only ſee God,</hi> our Saviour has told us, and they only care to ſee him. That this Veil then might be taken off from the Sinner's Heart, the chief part of Chriſt's Salvation was to ſave his People from their Sins, not only by making Atonement and Reconciliation for them, but by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the Pollution, Purging the Soul by Grace, and ſo qualifying it for the State of Light from which he deſcended, to acquaint the World plainly with the happy News of it.</p>
            <p>He that came from the boſom of God,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſt knew his Mind, has aſſured us upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that there is a Life after this, an Eternal Life of Happineſs beyond expreſſion, and preſent Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, provided for all Saints, for all that will live anſwerable to the holy Profeſſion of Chriſtianity. So much of that State and Condition at preſent is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd as is requiſite to excite attention and obedience in all that have Ears to hear. It comes with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Evidence to ſatisfie ſober Inquirers, that are contented <hi>to be wiſe unto Salvation.</hi> The Goſpel of God has been adorn'd by the Example of many ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65791:4"/>Children of Wiſdom who have gone before us in the Faith; many that have ſuffer'd the loſs of all things, the worſt that this World could inflict, the Madneſs, the Wit of Cruelty, in hopes of a great recompence of Reward; many I ſay, whole Clouds of ſuch Witneſſes as the Apoſtle ſtiles them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their numbers.</p>
            <p>That, by the grace of God, we may be enabled at this time to make ſome advance towards that ſtate of Light and Happineſs, by becoming in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree more qualified for the partaking of it, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to Diſcourſe on theſe Words in this Method.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To conſider the Nature of the State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints in the other World. It is here ſet forth as a State of <hi>Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The Certainty of it, the ſure Title they have to it: It is their <hi>Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The Qualifications requiſite to <hi>make them meet to partake</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. How theſe Qualifications are to be obtain'd; that ſo we may upon good grounds, <hi>give thanks unto God, who has made us meet to be partakers of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Saints in Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the Firſt; The Conſideration of the State and Condition of the Saints, here ſignified by a State of Light.</p>
            <p>Light is the moſt proper word to expreſs a State of Happineſs, and ſet forth to us the Heavenly State
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65791:5"/>and Condition, in whatever ſenſe we take the word <hi>Light;</hi> whether</p>
            <p>(1.) In its common or natural Senſe, for a Bodily Quality, a viſible Luſtre or Glory. Or, (2.) For Knowledge, which is ſometimes call'd Light. Or, (3.) For Purity and Holineſs; they are all of them Ingredients of the Heavenly State, and concurr to compleat its happineſs.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt;</p>
            <p>If <hi>Light</hi> be taken in its vulgar ſenſe for a viſible Luſtre and Glory, Light ſeems in this ſenſe to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to the Notion of Heaven; for Heaven is the Seat, the Country of Light. The Sun and Stars are Bodies Great and Glorious, yet theſe are but the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the outer Court of Heaven, ſerving to Beautifie and Enlighten the lower World: For the Heavenly Palace, the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> ſtiles it, <hi>the Seat of God, and of the bleſſed Spirits,</hi> that ſtands not in need of theſe Lights, they ſhine not there, they have no influence above. The Divine Apoſtle (<hi>Rev.</hi> 21.) has collected every thing that appears at preſent moſt bright and gay to help us to conceive the Glories of that Heavenly City. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents its Walls and Gates as built of the moſt gliſtring Pearls and Precious Stones, as paved with Gold; that there is no Night, but a perpetual Day; no need of Sun or Moon, for the Glory of God does enlighten it, for God is Light, and the Lamb is the Light thereof, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. The Light of the Sun would ſully and defile the pure brightneſs of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that being fitted only to ſerve the uſes of this Elementary World, is a groſs Light, a meer Kitchin-Fire, if compared to that moſt refined Light
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65791:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>with which God is Cloathed as with a Garment; Light inacceſſible to us in our preſent Capacities, but thoſe that ſhall be thought meet to be admitted into that State of Light (I pray God it may be the happy Lot of all here preſent) they ſhall have their Organs ſtrengthned, fitted to approach and enjoy that Light.</p>
            <p>For they themſelves ſhall be Cloath'd with Light, and dreſs'd up in the Habit of the Country; their Earthly Tabernacles ſhall be transform'd into Glorious Bodies, ſuch as their Saviour wears now in Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43.</note> for they ſhall ſhine then <hi>as Suns in the Kingdom of their Father</hi> he has aſſured them. Their Bodies ſhall be like the Glorious Body of Chriſt, tho' not equal to it in Glory.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Saints themſelves there ſhall be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Magnitude, as <hi>one Star differs from another in Glory. They that turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi> (12.3.) <hi>ſhall ſhine as Stars for ever and ever;</hi> and they eſpecially that have Suffer'd with Chriſt, ſhall be alſo Glorified with him. They that thought nothing too dear for their God, but had the Grace and Courage to Die for their Saviour, as he had Died for them, their mangled Bodies ſhall ſhine next to his in Glory.</p>
            <p>This imperfect Account of that State of Light may ſuggeſt to us the Happineſs of it, for Light is pleaſant to behold; it is ſo much the experience of every one that has Eyes to behold it, as that I need not quote <hi>Solomon</hi> for it. Light gives Beauty to all things, it is the Paint and Varniſh of the World, it is the Life of it; for when Light breaks in upon us, it awakens and gives new Life to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65791:6"/>Soul, it brisks the Spirits, and puts them in Tune for Joy and Mirth.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the Contrary, by <hi>Darkneſs</hi> is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied a State of Melancholy and Miſery. The Scene of Grief and Sorrow is black, the Afflicted ſhut out the Light, and condemn themſelves to Darkneſs. Darkneſs is a ſad ingredient of the Miſeries of Hell, it is the eſſential Character of that place of horrour; for the melancholy abode of the Damned is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd to us, by a Dungeon of Darkneſs, of utter extream Darkneſs, the very blackneſs of Darkneſs. This makes the Sorrows of that Place more oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the Spirit, its terrors more frightful and amazing. Beſides, Darkneſs gives ſcope and liberty to the Rage of guilty Conſciences. We know by woful experience, that our thoughts are always moſt tyrannical in the Dark, and ſting moſt ſeverely when any thing lies croſs or heavy upon the Spirit. Then when the Soul has nothing to do, but to think, has no Pleaſure to divert it, nor the too common refuge of Drink to drown its Cares, nor the leaſt pretence of Buſineſs to employ it for a moment. The <hi>ſteady</hi> remembrance then of the mad follies of a brutiſh Life, being reflected on in the Dark to all Eternity, and continually repeated with freſh vexation of Spirit, muſt of neceſſity ſtrike deep, pierce to the quick, and wound to the very Centre of the Soul. One Proſpect of that State of Darkneſs, one ſerious thought of it would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach us what abundant reaſon they have to give God thanks (as my Text exhorts) who are, by the Grace of God, made meet to be <hi>Partakers of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Saints in Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65791:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> (2.) <hi>Light</hi> is frequently put for <hi>Knowledge;</hi> in this reſpect alſo the State of the Saints in Heaven may properly be ſtiled a State of Light. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is Spiritual Light; it has the ſame influence upon the Eye of the Mind, as Light upon the Eye of the Body. Knowledge is pleaſant as Light, it cheers the Soul, it brings in Day upon it; it opens the World as Light, and gives a proſpect even to the utmoſt ends of the Earth. It ſees into the very Heavens, it takes in paſt and future Ages into its view, and by the help of Revelation even Eternity it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Knowledge gives Confidence and Security; the underſtanding Man goes on freely, and cheerfully, as he that Travels in the Day. He is in no danger of being led aſide by Shadows, and falſe Lights, whereas Ignorance and Darkneſs hide and ſhut up every thing in Obſcurity. The Ignorant Man is like one locked up in a cloſe Room, or that walks in the dark Night; he has no proſpect of Things about him, he knows not whither he goes, he ſtumbles, and wanders, and fears every ſtep, all the Dangers that a benighted Fancy can repreſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Knowledge</hi> is often expreſs'd by <hi>Light</hi> in the Holy Scriptures. Particularly the Goſpel-Revelation is Emphatically called <hi>the Light;</hi> and he that brought this Wonderful Diſcovery to the World, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore himſelf ſtiled the <hi>Light of the World,</hi> enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning every Man coming into it.</p>
            <p>And yet tho' the Goſpel Revelation be a great Light, in reſpect of all the Diſcoveries which were made before; inſomuch, as the Ancient Father well obſerv'd, the very Children of Chriſtians are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65791:7"/>in their Catechiſms taught to ſtammer forth greater Myſteries and ſublimer Truths than the Wiſeſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers could ever arrive to the Knowledge of; yet this bright Revelation is but dark in reſpect of Viſion: We do as yet <hi>ſee but as through a Glaſs darkly;</hi> we have a good Right, Title, and ſure Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but Promiſes are but Glimpſes in reſpect of Enjoyment, and that full Poſſeſſion with which the Saints in Heaven are inveſted. That therefore is well ſtiled a State of Light, becauſe a State of moſt certain, inlarged and exalted Knowledge.</p>
            <p>The State of this Life is really a State of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we ſee but in part. Truth is infinite, as God. A ſmall portion of it is allotted us at preſent; we know no more of it, than God is pleas'd to let us into. So much of it as may be uſeful to entertain us here, and to ſecure our Eternal Intereſts here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>But the Darkneſs of this State I now complain of, is what <hi>Sin</hi> has brought upon our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, diſturbing our Judgments, and poſſeſſing us with infinite variety of wild and abſurd Opinions; to that exceſs, as that it has paſs'd into a Proverb, <hi>So many Men, ſo many Minds.</hi> We might multiply much farther, for it is ſeldom long that the ſame Man continues in the ſame Mind. An infallible Argument of Darkneſs, for Truth is always one and the ſame, whatever differs from that muſt be Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Darkneſs. The Wiſeſt Men are here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to have their blind ſides, ſome miſtakes for which they have been remarked. All Men have Motes in their Eyes, ſome have Beams. It is too Notorious what ſenſeleſs Errors ſome have eſpouſed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65791:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>(the Particulars are innumerable) and maintain'd with heat and fierceneſs, to the great diſturbance of the World, and confuſion of the Church of God. It might be ſomething pardonable, if we diſcover'd our Weakneſs only in Tattle, and common Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, when we profeſs to unbend our Souls; but what Abominations do we ſee in the very Worſhip of the greateſt part of the World? What ridiculous Follies and Idolatries are to be found even at Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Altars. Their Underſtandings muſt needs want Light, that play the Fool with their God. When Men would be thought Wiſe, Serious, and Profound, how often do they betray the nakedneſs of their Souls. Our very Libraries are full of the blemiſhes of Mankind. And the Works of the Learned are too often ſtanding Monuments of the defects of Human Underſtanding. We ſmile and pity the rude ignorance or ſhort-ſightedneſs of thoſe that went before us, but their Cauſe will be revenged; (truſt an ill-natur'd World for it) when thoſe that follow us will laugh at ours. But the comfort is, we live in hopes of a better ſtate of Life; when every Man's Brain will be ſettled, and all Heads ſet right. When the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhall next appear, he will infallibly teach us all things. He will then conduct all thoſe to a State of <hi>pure Light and Knowledge,</hi> whom by his Grace, he has made meet to be Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of ſuch Happineſs. All miſts of Error will then be ſcatter'd by a clear Head, an impartial Reaſon, and fervent Charity. A State of pure Light and Knowledge therefore I call it.</p>
            <p>(1.) Becauſe there will be no Body, no Worldly Intereſt to cloud the Light of the Mind, or diſturb
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65791:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>it in its Reaſonings. No Fleſh and Blood enters that Kingdom; <hi>for the Natural Body</hi> we are aſſured <hi>will be rais'd a Spiritual Body;</hi> by which Phraſe we cannot well underſtand leſs than a more refined, a more exalted ſtate of Matter; far removed from its Original Clay; purified perhaps into Light, as near as poſſible into Spirit, that it may be a more ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Companion for the Rational Spirit of Man, a fit Partner of its Glories.</p>
            <p>(2.) A State of pure Light I call it, becauſe a State not of Revelation, but of Viſion. In a State of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation we know no more than the Revealer is pleas'd to diſcover, ſome Glimpſes only of things, the reſt often reſerv'd, or wrap'd up as Myſtery: But in Heaven the Saints are admitted to ſee with their own Eyes the naked Truth of Things. Then will be ſet to view the Wonders of Heaven; the Paſſages of Providence which are at preſent a Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, will be explain'd: The unfathomable depths of Divine Wiſdom; the unſearchable, and at preſent inconceiveable Riches of his Love and Kindneſs, will then be the Entertainment of our Souls; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of God which have been lock'd up from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, will then be laid open; ſo far at leaſt, as Creatures will be made capable of knowing them, or be made happy by them. Then may be infuſed New Ideas into the Underſtanding; for the want of which, thoſe things which are now therefore unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, may then be clear to our view. An Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Trinity, and a Trinity in Unity may poſſibly then be underſtood.</p>
            <p>(3.) A State of pure Light and Knowledge it will be, becauſe the Saints are there admitted into open
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65791:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and free Converſe with the Wiſeſt and Beſt of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, with the Renowned Worthies of all Ages: All thoſe Departed Souls that were Wiſe unto Salvation, with that innumerable Quire of Holy and Bleſſed Spirits, the Wiſe Angels of God; Laſtly, they are admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the Omniſcient God himſelf. Our Knowledge of his <hi>Creatures,</hi> which is but imperfect, (for it is but little that we know of the Myſteries of the Creation) and they themſelves but ſhadows of their Maker's Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Power, gives wonderful Delight at preſent, and is one of the moſt Raviſhing Entertainments our Reaſon is here acquainted with. How tranſporting then muſt that Light be, which ſhews the <hi>Creator</hi> himſelf face to face, and gives a <hi>cloſe</hi> view of all his Glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes in <hi>Subſtance,</hi> in Fulneſs and Perfection; where they live under the immediate and moſt powerful influence of them all, having the moſt lively and comfortable ſenſe of them continually injected into the Mind. For Spirits ſeem to Converſe by infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Thoughts and Affections, and the Goodneſs of God makes him always Communicative of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If we now conſider a thirſty Soul, a Spirit that has an inſatiable appetite after Knowledge, whoſe Thoughts are ſwifter than Lightning, plac'd not only in the proſpect of but <hi>united</hi> to a Being of infinite Perfections, a Being that can never be thought through, that can never be exhauſted by the Eternal thirſt of his Creatures, the contemplation of infinite Ages. How will ſuch a Soul continually increaſe in Knowledge, in brighter and brighter Light, 'till it kindles almoſt into a Seraphim; whither will ſuch a Spirit grow? I cannot tell what bounds to ſet to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65791:9"/>that Knowledge that is growing to all Eternity; nor how to meaſure the Powers of a Humane Soul in its State of Light and Enjoyment.</p>
            <p>If the Soul of Man then be ſuch a Wonderful Thing, capable of ſuch elevations of Spirit, of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Enjoyment; what pity is it, that God ſhould intruſt the greateſt part of Mankind with ſuch a precious Jewel? What pity is it that this Heaven-born Creature ſhould be ſuffer'd to trifle away its time here on Earth, and which is worſe, to wallow in Filth and Brutiſhneſs, and at laſt deſcend into Everlaſting Darkneſs, and Eternal Wailings, Curſing and Blaſpheming of that God, which it was made to Admire, and Adore, to Love and Praiſe to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>(3.) I haſten to the 3d Acception of <hi>Light,</hi> as it is taken for <hi>Purity</hi> of Heart, <hi>Holineſs of Life</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Practice: In this ſenſe alſo, the Inheritance of the Saints above is a State of Light, becauſe a State of the greateſt Purity.</p>
            <p>In this Senſe, our Saviour enjoyns us to take care that <hi>our Light ſo ſhine before Men, as that they may ſee our good Works,</hi> and by our bright Examples be directed and enlightned in the Paths they ſhould walk in; that by the Beauty of our Converſation they may be enamour'd and charm'd into a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and <hi>glorifie God</hi> by an ambitious imitation of our Wiſdom and Holineſs. Chriſtians are therefore ſtiled the <hi>Lights of the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.</note> the <hi>Children of the Light, and of the Day.</hi> In this ſenſe we find it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd by St. <hi>John,</hi> with a moſt pompous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; the four firſt Verſes being a ſolemn preparation to this great Truth, <hi>that God is Light</hi> (v. 5.) <hi>and in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65791:9"/>him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> to fully the brightneſs of his Underſtanding, no impurity to biaſs his Will; he hates it therefore, as being perfectly contrary to his pure Nature, <hi>what communion hath Light with Darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Impurity is indeed Darkneſs, it clouds the Mind which is tinctured with it, as we have ſeen already in Matters of Opinion or Doctrine; in practical Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters much more. In theſe eſpecially, the Fleſh having a greater intereſt and concern, the Soul of a Man is in greater danger of being benighted and fool'd, and often made to act contrary to the Principles of all good Reaſon. The inconſiſtencies and madneſs of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are every where notorious; their brutiſh and perverſe reaſonings and actings, eſpecially in moral Matters; their whole Life being a continued courſe of follies and ill humours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thine Eye be Evil,</hi> ſaith our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.23.</note> and the <hi>Light that is in thee be Darkneſs, how great is that Darkneſs?</hi> even as great as the Evil which is in the Eye, and bears always a proportion to the power of the reigning Luſt, being a reſult and effect of it. Hence it becomes ſo hard a thing amongſt us Sinners, to find that precious Jewel (ſo much talk'd of) <hi>Right Reaſon.</hi> Moſt certainly it is no where to be found, but in a purified Soul.</p>
            <p>The only Expedient therefore to reſtore Light to a Sinner's Soul, is to purifie it from its Luſts. For this Reaſon did Baptiſm anciently go under the Name of Illumination; as conveying the Holy Spirit with his Sanctifying Graces into the Soul; which do by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees enlighten it here in this Life, as it paſſes from one degree of Grace unto another, 'till at Death it is compleatly Sanctified, and fitted for its Heavenly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65791:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>State of Light; eſpecially when at the Morning of the Reſurrection it ſhall be dreſs'd up with its Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Glorified Body, which will then be no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to the Soul, as this Fleſhly Tabernacle is now, but will conſpire with it in its operations, in its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of God, in the perfect practice of Holineſs, and all the buſineſs of Heaven. There will be right Reaſon in Perfection, according to the extent of its Knowledge, no Darkneſs at all; the whole face of the Soul will be bright and clear, not one ſpot to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered there. This is a State of Light indeed. And let me farther obſerve, that in proportion as the Body was purified by Grace here in this Life, ſhall it be more refined, more Spiritual, and have brighter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Glory. Its ſight of God more clear, its communications from the Fountain of Light more ſtrong, having its Faculties extraordinarily ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened to behold the Glorious Godhead. The more pure Souls ſhall be peculiarly fitted to receive the ſtronger impreſſions of Divine Love.</p>
            <p>For the State of Light is a State of Love. If Love be the fulfilling of the Commandments, compleat Holineſs can be no other than perfect Love, the Top of Heavenly Happineſs. Love is the Beauty of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the Glory of God himſelf. God is Love, and God is Light; his Love and Favour is often expreſs'd in Scripture <hi>by the Light of his Countenance.</hi> Love has its Flames we all know, the Love of Saints eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially. For inexpreſſible are the tranſports of a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Soul, when admitted into the immediate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God; when it has a clear view given it of the beſt of Beings; when it has all Goodneſs for its Object, all Perfection. How quickly like Lightning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65791:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>its Affections are kindled! how vehemently! In a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is all on fire, and with an inflamed appetite flies to its moſt Beloved. Exceſſive Love placed upon a Creature is Torment, and does abuſe the Appetite, becauſe quickly drawn dry. But when God is the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Love cannot be exceſſive, there being enough in him to give Eternal Satisfaction. Thrice happy Souls, infinitely more than thrice happy, whoſe <hi>Buſineſs</hi> it is to love. They love always, they love vehemently, and yet can never, never love too much. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all this, if any thing can be more; a ſenſe of being beloved by God, of living always under the ſmile and ſhine of his Countenance. This indears all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Perfections, and gives them another Infinity.</p>
            <p>To be beloved by a Creature below our ſelves is very obliging, and does wonderfully draw forth our Affections to that little thing, what e'er it be. When the Great God then infuſes a ſenſe of his Love into the Soul, it tranſports it into ſuch an Extaſie as is fit only for the other World. Mortality cannot bear it, Mortality cannot conceive it. It is neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I ſtop here.</p>
            <p>So near as I can conceive, ſuch as this is that State of Light, that Inheritance of the Saints, the great Object of our Hopes, the Buſineſs of this Life, that we may be made meet to be partakers of it. If what has been Diſcourſed has raiſed in any Perſon deſires of being well aſſured of this State of Happineſs, I proceed.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, To conſider the <hi>Certainty</hi> we have of it; our good Title to it, it is call'd an <hi>Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Creation is the Family of God, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for it every day; he gives even the Ravens their food: But Man that was made after the Image of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65791:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, has a more particular Relation to him. By his Natural likeneſs he would have appear'd a true Son of God, had he preſerv'd his Original Character unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd. But what Man loſt by his Folly, God has mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully reſtor'd to him again by Grace. So that he who is by his Natural Birth now a Child of Wrath, is by his Spiritual Birth become a Child of God again. He is adopted Son and Heir of God, not for any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of his. There can be no pretence of merit in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Born to an Eſtate, and truly not more in being adopted Son of God. It was meer Grace, unprovoked Goodneſs. For whilſt Man continu'd in his Rebellion, whilſt in his Blood and Filth, God caſt his Love upon him. He paſt by thoſe Noble Creatures the Angels, for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf, to make Man his Son and his Heir too, by giving him a good Title to the Eſtate of God his Father, who is Lord of Heaven and Earth. Who would not be ambitious to be his Heir, who has ſuch large Patrimony to beſtow; not cantled into Portions, but every Heir has a Title to the whole. <hi>He that overcomes ſhall inherit all things:</hi> We are aſſured by the Infallible Charter, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7.) <hi>They ſhall Inherit the Earth,</hi> for none have ſo good a Title to the Creature, as thoſe who honour the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator. So much of the Earth they ſhall be ſure of, as their loving Father ſees beſt for them, and will beſt conſiſt with their Eternal Inheritance. For Heaven is the chief Patrimony of God.</p>
            <p>Here we live like Heirs under Age, under Tutors and Governors, 'till we are train'd up and fitted to have our Eſtate put into our hands, to be inveſted with the full Poſſeſſion of that vaſt Inheritance;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> where we are to be admitted as <hi>Joint Heirs</hi> to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65791:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Natural Son of God, partakers of the ſame Glories with himſelf, <hi>ſitting with him upon Thrones.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In this Life we have given us that ample Security that is fit for Heirs at preſent to have; ſufficient for our incouragement, our Immortal Inheritance being ſet before us in a clear Light. Eternal Life is not ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all the Heirs of Salvation by abſolute Decree; for it is plain, <hi>that many periſh for whom Chriſt died.</hi> And it will no doubt be an heavy-aggravation of the Damnation of Chriſtians, that they refuſed that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which they might have obtain'd, and ſold their Spiritual-Birth-right for a Meſs of Pottage. It will be the Sting of their Miſery that it was by their own fault that they fell ſhort, God having given all the Security that is fit for him to give. For we have (1.) His repeated <hi>Promiſes</hi> of Salvation to all that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and Repent; and ſooner ſhall Heaven and Earth fail, than one tittle of what he has promis'd. God <hi>ſo loved the World,</hi> his Promiſes are ſo very great to Sinners, as that they might appear incredible. We might with ſome colour of Reaſon ſtagger in our Faith, if we were not well aſſured of the Reality of his Promiſe. To help therefore our Infirmities, that we may not ſuſpect the goodneſs of his word, he has (2.) Confirm'd it by an <hi>Oath,</hi> that our Conſolation might be ſtrong,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.</note> having two immutable things to ſupport it, the Promiſe and the Oath of God. And yet theſe two things in themſelves unchangeable, for our more abundant ſecurity are (3.) farther confirm'd by the Blood of God, the Seal of the Covenant of this Eternal Life; it being an ancient way of making Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants inviolable by Sealing them with Blood. And laſtly, If it were poſſible for all theſe to fail us, this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65791:12"/>Covenant of God is Seal'd by the Spirit alſo, given as an Earneſt of our Eternal Inheritance. His Graces are not only Pledges, but part of Payment; <hi>the Glory of the Saints in Light</hi> being only Grace in perfection. Having ſo good reaſon to be well ſatisfied with our Title to this Inheritance, <hi>our next Concern</hi> then may be,</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, To Conſider of the Qualifications requiſite to <hi>make us meet to partake of it.</hi> The State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Place does ſufficiently diſcover how he ought to be qualified, that would be admitted into that Holy Place. <hi>No unclean thing can enter there;</hi> none can be happy there. The Light will ſhame and expoſe its filthineſs, and render every ſpot an Object of hatred and abhorrency to all the pure Inhabitants. All Works of Darkneſs would there appear monſtrous, whatever we either are, or ſhould be aſhamed of; what wants concealment and will not bear the Light, can never be fit for a ſtate of the pureſt Light. But yet we need not inquire who ſhall aſcend into Heaven for us, to view thoſe Regions of Happineſs, and bring down to us a Deſcription of the Place and Character of the Bleſſed Inhabitants. All that we need to know in this Caſe is very nigh us; the direct way to Heaven is in the Book of God, which we have in our hands, drawn out in plain Rules and Precepts, and if it be not our fault it is legible in our Hearts alſo.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, becauſe <hi>Examples</hi> are uſually more powerful, as having more of Life in them, than the dead Letter of a Precept; we have therefore in the Goſpel drawn out to the Life an Heir of Heaven.</p>
            <p>God ſhew'd us at firſt what manner of Men we ought to be, even ſuch as he made us at firſt, when we came pure out of his hands, when we were like
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65791:12"/>himſelf. For it is the Deſign of Religion to reduce us back again by the Methods of Grace, as near as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to our Primitive Original State; to Sanctifie and make us clean, even Innocent once again if it might be. However, to come as near to Innocence as our preſent State of Fleſh and Blood will permit.</p>
            <p>If much of that State of Innocence is not to be learnt from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by reaſon of his ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in that Original State, in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> we have a compleat Pattern, it being the great Deſign of his coming from Heaven, at leaſt of his living ſo long upon the Earth, that he might ſhew the way thither by his Example.</p>
            <p>He gave us therefore the Pattern of a moſt Holy, and for the moſt part of a very imitable Life. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued practice of thoſe Vertues with which he would have his Followers to be exercis'd and diſtinguiſh'd, and train'd up for their Heavenly Inheritance. We may thence learn the whole Duty of Man, towards God, and every Perſon.</p>
            <p>For he did truly <hi>Love God,</hi> as he requires us to do, <hi>with all his Heart and Soul,</hi> God <hi>was in all his thoughts.</hi> It was therefore his conſtant indeavour to do what he knew to be <hi>moſt pleaſing to him.</hi> It <hi>was his meat and drink to do the will of his Father, to work the work of him that ſent him while it was day, before the night came.</hi> When but Twelve Years Old, he ſlip'd from his Secular Parents, that he might ſpend ſome time in <hi>his Father's Houſe,</hi> or as we tranſlate it, <hi>be about his Father's Buſineſs.</hi> Knowing what was wrote in the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of God's Book, he voluntarily came to do his Will; ſeeing it highly pleaſing to his Father that loſt Mankind ſhould be Redeem'd, he freely offer'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65791:13"/>to the Work, tho' they were bitter things that the incenſed Father required of Man's Surety; But ſo that God might be glorified, it pleas'd him to become an Object of the greateſt Miſery and Contempt. To give us an Example of an intire dependance upon the Providence of God, and truſt in him, he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf poor, deſtitute of Worldly Comfort and Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; <hi>the Foxes have holes, but he had not where to lay his head.</hi> He could indeed <hi>turn ſtones into Bread,</hi> but we do not read that ever he work'd a Miracle to ſuſtain his own hunger, but truſted himſelf intirely to his Father's keeping. 'Tis true, he complain'd with loud paſſion upon the Croſs, but not from deſpair, or the leaſt miſtruſt of God's failing him; for with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence he <hi>commended his Spirit into his hands;</hi> but a quick ſenſe he had of that unuſual change in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Countenance. It touch'd him to the quick, that the beloved Father ſhould look ſo full of Anger upon his moſt beloved Son: It was the ſting of his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to ſee a Cloud and ſevere Frown upon that Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Face, which always uſed to ſhine upon him with a pleaſing Aſpect; now eſpecially whilſt he knew himſelf to be performing an Act highly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to his Father.</p>
            <p>Obſerve yet farther, and imitate; his Converſation was in Heaven whilſt here on Earth, his heart always there, his Diſcourſes tended thither, Heavenly things being ever predominant in his Thoughts; he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to take fit Occaſions to improve all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences to Spiritual Purpoſes, and raiſe up the Minds of his Company to the things above. He ſought opportunities of Retirement, that he might have frequent and immediate Converſe with God his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65791:13"/>Father. Thoſe hours wherein Nature call'd for Eaſe and Sleep, he very often imploy'd in his Devotions, ſpending whole Nights in Prayer. He ſat looſe from the World, perfectly dead to it, The great and moſt difficult Leſſon of Religion. He had no affection for the things of it, they appear'd not worth his thoughts. But yet his contempt of them was decent and generous; he did not with proud diſdain ſpurn at them as a rude Stoick would have done, he did not affront Men of Quality and Title, but paid all becoming reſpect to thoſe Honours of the World, which he had not ſuch regard for, as to aſſume them to himſelf. In his common Converſation he was very obliging, affable, courteous, always in good humour, converſing freely, even with the worſt of Men, <hi>with Publicans and Sinners,</hi> to make them if poſſible, wiſer and better. He was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſpoſed to put the moſt fair and candid interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Behaviour of Men, ready to make the beſt excuſes for them that their Caſe would admit of, with any tolerable ſhew or colour of Reaſon; willing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their faults and neglects to infirmity, the <hi>weakneſs of their Fleſh</hi> or Mind, rather than to Malice, or ill deſign.</p>
            <p>When the Caſe would admit of no excuſe, but he was treated with the vileſt uſage, and ill language, yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled not again, but by cool and good argument indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to convince them of their Blaſphemy and Outrage. How calmly did he receive even <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf in an Act of the baſeſt Treachery, with the Title of <hi>Friend, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art thou come?</hi> When his mind was loaded with grief, to that extremity that he <hi>ſweat drops of Blood,</hi> no murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, fretful or diſcontented word dropt from him, he retain'd his Temper as well as his Integrity. When he hung upon the Croſs in moſt exceſſive pain, no uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit appear'd, but he was quietly ſubmiſſive to his Father's Will. His whole Life was a conſtant courſe of Charity, always doing good to the Bodies or Souls of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65791:14"/>Men; <hi>healing their Diſeaſes, raiſing their Dead to Life,</hi> and at laſt dying himſelf an accurſed Death, that his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, his Enemies that uſed him deſpitefully, that hated him to the death, might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>This is our Calling, Chriſtians, this is our Pattern, <hi>Let us go and do likewiſe.</hi> If we can thus live, if we can thus love, then are we <hi>meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi> But if the Caſe be thus with us, we may begin with amazement to cry out, <hi>who then can or ſhall be ſaved?</hi> We ſeem to have reaſon to fear that our Saviour has undone us by his Example; has carried the Mark ſo high, and propos'd ſuch Conditions of Salvation as Fleſh and Blood can never reach to, can never hope upon theſe terms to be made meet <hi>partakers of the Heavenly Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, It highly concerns us therefore to inquire, if they be poſſible,</p>
            <p>How theſe Qualifications are to be obtain'd.</p>
            <p>In a word, it is true that Fleſh and Blood, Corrupt Fleſh and Blood eſpecially, can never advance to that pitch of Holineſs as to live as our Saviour lived, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by its own ſtrength (we may be ſure) fit it ſelf for an admittance into that high and Holy Place. But the Comfort is, we do not go forth in our own ſtrength, we have the ſame Spirit of God promis'd and given to every baptiz'd Chriſtian, which ſanctified our Lord Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and inabled him to walk as he walk'd. 'Tis true, he had the Spirit of God given him in much greater meaſure,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9.</note> and was <hi>anointed above all his fellows</hi> (as the Apoſtle has taught us to ſpeak) whether Angels or Men, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing and perfecting of all kind of Vertue and Holineſs; and tho' it may not conſiſt with the method of God's Grace, and our preſent State and Condition, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſhould act ſo powerfully in us; yet if it be not our own fault, he will certainly act as <hi>effectually,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us ſufficient ſtrength for the doing of what is requiſite
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65791:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>in order to Salvation, and by degrees will lead us on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that perfection, as will fit us to <hi>dwell with the Saints above.</hi> The difficulty of the Work can give us no juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to deſpair, when we have a God working in us, and will not fail to do his part: But yet, tho' nothing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible with God, and he will not fail us, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for us to do in this great Work; there lies our Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, therefore there ought to be our Care. The Advice which I ſhall briefly offer ſhall be this, and ſo Conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be very Conſtant and Diligent in the uſe of thoſe Means which the Goſpel has preſcribed; For a Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Heaven is not a Fitt, but a laſting Temper of the Mind, which is only to be obtain'd by a Conſtancy in Religious Practice. Let every Morning and Evening at leaſt have its fix'd times for Private Devotion, with ſerious application of Mind: Let us every day look over and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine well our Account between God and our own Souls. This is an excellent Expedient to make ſhort Reckonings at laſt. He that makes even with God every day by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, is every night qualified for Heaven, and has but one day to account for, when ever he dies.</p>
            <p>Read ſome part of the Word of God, digeſt it well by Meditation, this ſupplies the Soul with its daily Food; for <hi>Spirits</hi> muſt be nouriſh'd as well as <hi>Bodies;</hi> be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually fed with good Thoughts, or they will languiſh, or which is worſe, grow Brutiſh and Deviliſh. In their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seaſons, Publick Ordinances are to be duly attended, and more Solemn times of Self-examination fix'd; but I lay the greateſt ſtreſs of Religion upon thoſe private daily Performances. In the neglect of theſe, it is impoſſible to be Religious in earneſt, and keep up a true Spirit of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is difficult to perſwade to theſe, but they being once ſecured, the reſt will eaſily follow. The Goſpel-Means are not empty dead Ceremonies, like thoſe of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65791:15"/>Law, they are <hi>Living Ordinances,</hi> they are Bodies with a Soul, for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> accompanies the due performance of them; which as at firſt convey'd with the waters of Baptiſm to the Soul; ſo by every Sermon, Prayer or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rightly perform'd, takes freſh poſſeſſion, and comes in with new degrees of ſtrength. A diligent uſe of theſe means of Religion are therefore neceſſary, as being the only way to obtain and ſecure this Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Keep your Eye always fix'd upon your Inheritance, having his Eye upon the <hi>recompence of the Reward,</hi> anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our Saviour himſelf to go through with his difficult Undertaking. This is one of the peculiar Advantages of the Goſpel, that the Gates of Heaven are in a manner ſet open to us, and ſuch a view given into thoſe Regions of Happineſs, as is ſufficient to excite to Duty, and keep us in our way thither. More knowledge of Heaven might do hurt at preſent, might exalt us into rapture and extaſie, and make us impatient of tarrying here. God has there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely proportion'd theſe Diſcoveries to our preſent Circumſtances and Neceſſities. It concerns us to make a right uſe of this peculiar benefit of the Goſpel, never to loſe the ſight of Heaven which it affords. <hi>All the Kingdoms of the Earth, and Glory of them,</hi> are not ſufficient to make an impreſſion upon that Mind that is full of Heaven. He walks therefore with the World under his feet, having his Heart always with his Treaſure above; and he that lives above the World at preſent, where ſhould he live but in Heaven hereafter?</p>
            <p>Being by the Grace of God, thus <hi>made meet to be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> let him give thanks to the Father, and with joyful Lips bleſs his Holy Name, and begin his Eternal Praiſes.</p>
            <closer>To God the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghoſt, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory, now, and for Evermore.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65791:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
